Zakiullah Khan Mohammed

Phone: +91 8977118511 E-Mail: mail@khanio.com Web: http://www.khanio.com Twitter: @khan_io GitHub: khanio

Summary

Since starting out with a 286 IBM machine in 1992 at the age of 8, I have been a technology guy with a penchant for the web and data, big and small. I love starting things from scratch and a big believer in simplicity and continuous learning. 6+ years of technical management (co-located, remote, and offshore) experience in software development/support/maintenance (on premise and SaaS), recruiting, planning, performance management, mentoring/coaching, production environments management and internal and external stakeholder/vendor/customer management.

I am comfortable with handling project and product management or system engineering at a large enterprise; and equally competent with being a CTO or a Director for Engineering at a relatively young start-up, leading the engineering team with a breadth of experience building practical, functional, and rich experience applications. In the foreseeable future, however, I would want to expand my interest into the research domain — applying technology in all its facets, not just for its business value, but also for its social impact.

Specialties

Pre-Sales Management

Agile Project Management

Proof-of-Concept/Prototype Engineering

A !! AA !! . ! . / COD!!!! A C. ! .

Query Systems (SQL, Hive, Pig, Impala)

- Solution Architectures
- User Experience Engineering
- Software Development Management

3+ years' experience

Skills

•	Agile Methodologies (SCRUM & Kanban)	5+ years' experience
•	Information Architecture (Adobe Photoshop / Microsoft Office / Enterprise Architect)	5+ years' experience
•	Public & Private Cloud Computing (Amazon Web Services / OpenStack)	4+ years' experience
•	Programming Languages (C / Python / Scala)	5+ years' experience
•	Web Scripting (HTML / CSS / JavaScript / Less)	5+ years' experience
•	Web Frameworks (Django / Flask / Play / NodeJS Express)	5+ years' experience
•	RESTFul API Framework (Spray using Typesafe Akka)	2+ years' experience
•	Messaging Systems (RabbitMQ / ZeroMQ)	2+ years' experience
•	Distributed Computing (OpenMPI / Hadoop / Spark)	3+ years' experience
•	Statistical Computing & Data Mining (R / Octave)	3+ years' experience
•	General Purpose GPU Computing (CUDA)	1+ years' experience
•	Data Integration (Pentaho ETL)	3+ years' experience
•	Business Intelligence (Pentaho BI / JasperSoft)	3+ years' experience
•	In-Memory Computing (SAP HANA / GridGrain)	2+ years' experience
•	Database Systems	4+ years' experience
	(MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, Apache Cassandra, Apache HBase, Google BigQuery)	

Experience

Interim CTO @ Remitgram, Inc. - Palo Alto

Nov 2013 - Present

Remitgram Inc., is an early-stage start-up based out of Palo Alto, which is focused on redefining how one sends money to friends and family living in India. Using Remitgram, consumers can send money via direct bank deposit to Recipient in real-time and cost-effective way.

Responsible for solution & information architecture, design, engineering and processes created as intellectual property, to deliver a cross platform solution which is scalable, elastic and operates on AWS stack.

Software Engineering Management Consultant @ Independent – Kuala Lumpur

Oct 2012 - Oct 2013

Educational Media Objects (EduMo), a seed round funded start-up established to deliver an online adaptive learning platform for schools, where in the school administration, teachers, students, parents and tutors can collaborate and assess student's performance.

EduMo Learning Management System is offered as a SaaS to its customers, and integrates schools, independent content development vendors and students, and relies heavily on Rich Media for delivering immersive learning experience. My responsibilities include but not limited to, technical direction on solution architecture, overseeing agile software development process, working with various line of business (LOB), program manager and product owner on requirement/design/integration of software components, providing production support, designed & developed business critical web service components and resource management including technical talent acquisition, mentoring and coaching.

Technical Director @ Cosmopoint SDN. BHD - Kuala Lumpur

Nov 2011 - Oct 2012

The Cosmopoint Group of Companies provides industry-based higher education and career-oriented training programme and services. The Group aims to create a strong presence across the ASEAN region in delivering quality education for various industrial disciplines that offers practical learning experience.

The SaaS and on premise versions of the TuitionMaster, Platform, which consisted of a Learning Management System (LMS), Learning Content Management System (LCMS), and an ERP implementation. My responsibilities include but not limited to, providing technical direction on platform and technology selection, agile software development process, plan and implement new significantly improved systems and services, working with internal and external technology groups to design integration software components, working with IT infrastructure team on software/hardware configuration/monitoring, product release and deployment activities, working with HR on technical talent acquisition.

Principal Consultant / MD @ Esberi Technologies Private Limited - Chennai / Bangalore May 2006 - Oct 2011

Esberi Technologies Private Limited, started as a 3 person boutique consulting firm focused around Rich Internet Applications Engineering and grew quickly to be a renowned Adobe Solution Partner in the sub-continent region. At its peak with 35 person staff, working out of two offices, it catered to small and big customers like SAP, Nissan, Invtirogen, Elba Print, Photo.com, and Govt. of Dubai.

Responsible for entity setup, human capital development, practice management, solution architectures, software development management and single handedly taking care of account acquisition worth 0.3 Million USD. Had the privilege to work on-site with customers in US, Germany, France, UAE and Singapore, who were either Fortune 500 or young startup companies.

^{**} Kindly note Project Portfolio and References available on request.

Education

•	Online Coursework - Data Science Specialization - Johns Hopkins University	2014		
•	Online Coursework – Machine Learning – Stanford University	2013		
•	Global Growth Program for Entrepreneurs – Indian School of Business	2009		
•	Bachelors in Electronics & Communications Engineering – Anna University	2007		
•				
Ce	ertifications			
•	Certified SCRUM Master	2014		
•	AWS Solution Architect – Associate Level	2014		
•	Cloudera Certified Professional: Data Scientist	2014		
Presentations				
•	Designing Big Data Solutions using AWS – FSecure - Kuala Lumpur	2013		
•	Designing Big Data Solutions using AWS – FSecure - Kuala Lumpur Bootstrapping Machine Learning – Singapore ML User Group	2013 2012		
•	Bootstrapping Machine Learning – Singapore ML User Group	2012		
•	Bootstrapping Machine Learning – Singapore ML User Group Functional Programming using Scala – Esberi Sponsored Online Webinar	2012 2011		
•	Bootstrapping Machine Learning – Singapore ML User Group Functional Programming using Scala – Esberi Sponsored Online Webinar Keynote – Enterprise Applications Using LiveCycle Services - Adobe Flash Platform Summit – Bangalore	2012 2011 2010		
•	Bootstrapping Machine Learning – Singapore ML User Group Functional Programming using Scala – Esberi Sponsored Online Webinar Keynote – Enterprise Applications Using LiveCycle Services - Adobe Flash Platform Summit – Bangalore Deep Dive with Flex Data Services - The ActionScript Conference – Singapore	2012 2011 2010 2009		

Associations

- The Indus Entrepreneurs (TiE) Hyderabad Chapter
- Indian School of Business CEE Alumni
- USENIX + LISA group
- Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)

- Institute for Electrical & Electronics Engineers (IEEE)
- SCRUM Alliance Network
- DZone Most Valuable Blogger Network

Open Source Contributions

Project Amada – An Apache Shiro based standalone authentication, authorization and session management server, which can be used to secure web, mobile and RESTFul API applications. It consists of three components and all are licensed under MIT license:

- amada-server A core server built using Typesafe technologies and tools like Scala, Slick, Akka and Spray with Apache Shiro support.
- amada-cli A command line interface tool to access and work with kanji-server locally or remotely, built using Python.
- amada-console A web interface to provide kanji-server administration tasks, built using NodeJS, ExpressJS and SocketJS.

Personal Facts

- Born on 13th May, 1984.
- Started programming using BASIC at the age of 8 years using 286 IBM Machine.
- Represented CBSE South Zone for Hockey, and played Soccer at School & University level.
- Awarded best final year project "Autonomous Vehicle Navigation Simulation using Neural Networks" by Crescent Engineering College.
- Honored by B.S Abdur Rahman University for Outstanding Young Entrepreneur 2009.
- Currently holding valid B1 (Business Visit Pass) for United States of America valid till 2019.
- Interested in history, politics, technology, and travelling.

Permanent Address

House No. 12-2-799/17, Mehdipatnam, Hyderabad 500028, AP, India.